How to be a great voiceover artist. No
experience needed. Maybe you've always
liked audiobooks or possibly character
work in animation or video games and
thought, "Hey, I'd like to be able to do
that." Well, here's the good news. You
absolutely can. Yes, you. You don't need
years of acting school, although that
does help, or a broadcasting degree, and
you definitely don't need to live in LA
or New York anymore. You can do it right
from where you live. In today's world,
as long as you've got a voice and a
working internet connection, you can do
this job from anywhere in the world.
Once again, being a good voice actor is
not about having a nice voice. It's
about being able to connect with the
listener. You have to treat your voice
like an instrument. You have to also
have some technical knowhow. And then
lastly, and most importantly, you have
to treat it like a business. So, in this
video, I'm going to take you through the
steps you need to know about how to get
started as a voice actor. even if you
have no experience. We're going to cover
what voice acting actually is and what
it isn't, the different types of work
available, how to train your voice even
if you haven't acted a day in your life,
the basic equipment you need and how to
go about it without overspending, how to
set up a simple home studio, some
performance tips to keep you sounding
natural and real, and finally, how to go
about landing paid work without any
experience. So, by the end, you're going
to have a road map on how to become a
voice actor and how to actually be good
at it. So, let's dive in. So, when most
people think of voice acting, they think
of maybe the movie trailer guy. You
know, the guy that's like in a world.
Well, there's a whole lot more to voice
acting than that. Voice acting is really
just telling a story or guiding someone
through some steps or entertaining
someone. Think about going through your
day and how many times you hear a
disembodied voice telling you something.
Maybe it's commercials on TV or on the
radio or on YouTube, audiobooks and
podcasts, e-learning courses or training
videos for companies, animation or video
game characters, GPS apps or phone
systems, even Tik Tok and Instagram
reels. If you think about it, we are
surrounded by voiceovers every single
day. Have you ever gone to get gas and
at the pump there's a screen there that
tells you the local headlines or maybe
the weather forecast? Someone actually
got paid to do that and you could too.
Modern clients these days, they want
voices that are real and natural and can
connect to their listener. Now, why do
you think that is? It's because clients
trust authenticity. So, if you're
sitting there thinking, "Well, I don't
sound like Morgan Freeman or Scarlett
Johansson." That's totally fine. You
don't have to anymore. Being a great
voice actor isn't about imitating
someone else. It's about finding your
own unique voice and using that voice as
your instrument to connect to the
listener. Okay. Now, let's talk about
the kind of voiceover work that's out
there that you can actually get. So,
here are some of the main categories.
The first up would be commercials.
That's what most people think of when
they hear voice over, and that's
commercials on TV or the radio or
streaming platforms, maybe on YouTube or
Tik Tok. those commercials that tell you
to buy this car or use this type of
dishwasher detergent. Next up is
narration, and that would be things like
e-learning or company training videos or
maybe documentaries. These are longer
form reads that are less punchy and
quick and are more about informing the
listener. The next category is
audiobooks. Right now, audiobooks are
exploding thanks to platforms like
Audible and Amazon and Spotify. Getting
into audiobooks right now is a huge
opportunity for voice actors. Next up is
animation and video games. This is
probably the most fun category in
voiceover. This is giving characters
their voice on your favorite animation
series or your favorite video game
series. This is where your acting chops
really come into play. What about
telefan or IVR systems? IVR stands for
interactive voice response, which is
really just phone systems. Press one for
sales, press two for support. someone
gets paid to record those. Each one of
these categories, and by the way, those
are just the top ones. There's plenty
more than that. Each one of these
requires a different skill set of
acting. But here's the best part.
There's no need to pick one of these
niches right away. Let the market
decide. I always advise people when
they're first getting into voice acting
is try everything out. See what sticks.
See what you enjoy doing. Because if you
enjoy doing it, it's going to be a lot
easier for you to do it. The bottom line
is there's room for every kind of voice
in voice acting. Young, old, male,
female, and anybody else. If you've got
a voice and you can make people believe
what you're saying, you're in the club.
>> And now for something completely
different.
>> If you've always wanted to get into
voiceover and especially recording
audiobooks, then you don't want to miss
our upcoming monthly master class. This
month, it's all about audiobooks with
our special guest, top audiobook
narrator, Tom Parks. Tom has recorded
over 800 titles, including the
best-selling personal finance book, Rich
Dad Poor Dad. Tom will also be diving
deep into how to grow and maintain your
audiobook business. Whether you're a
beginner or you just want to make more
money recording audiobooks. This live
class is coming up on September 23rd,
2025 at 8:00 p.m. Eastern time, 5:00
p.m. Pacific. Seats are limited to a
100red attendees because we need to make
sure that we answer all the questions
that come up during the class. The class
will also be recorded, so when you sign
up, you'll always have that class that
you can refer back to. If you can't make
it to the live class, the replay is
going to be available after the class,
just not at the discounted rate. So, if
you want the lowest price and to be
there live, click on the link in the
description and pin comment below. Oh,
one last thing. Every month I always do
a drawing to win a free seat to the
class. So, when you enter, you're
automatically entered into that drawing.
See you there.
>> And now, back to your regularly
scheduled program.
>> All right. How do you actually train
your voice to be professional? You don't
need to be born with some sort of radio
voice to do voice acting. You just need
the three C's. Control, clarity, and
connection. Let's break it down into
three parts. The first part is warm-ups
and breath control. Just like athletes
when they warm up before a big match or
a big game, it's important for you to
warm up your voice before diving right
into your first job of the day. Now, you
can either just hum, you can pull up
your first script of the day and read it
out loud just to warm up your vocal
cords. I actually call my mom most
mornings just to check on her, but that
also helps me warm up my vocal cords
before I jump into that ver first
project of the day. Next up is clarity
and diction. Now, I'm not saying you
should overinunciate every single word.
In fact, that's what a lot of people
think voice acting is when they first
start reading scripts is they try to be
perfect. And perfect is the enemy. You
want to be clear but not stiff. Next up
is acting without overacting. A lot of
people when they first sit down to
behind a microphone, when they first hit
record, they switch gears into their
acting voice and everything becomes
stiff and polished and different from
how they normally act. Sure, it's
acting, but it's very subtle. Remember,
you don't have your facial expressions
or you don't have big movements to get
your point across. All you have is your
voice. Here's how you can train your
voice and and get used to hearing your
own voice. A lot of people when they
first hear their voice, they are taken
aback and they're like, "Wow, I didn't
know I sounded like that." Well, that's
there's some biology there where the
shape of the skull makes us sound
differently to ourselves than other
people, and that's normal, but it will
get better as you do it. You'll get more
and more used to hearing your own voice.
For practice, record yourself every day
and play it back and listen critically.
Are there mouth clicks and mouth pops,
extraneous breaths? Are you actually
reading the copy off the script or are
you actually saying it? There's a
difference between reading it and saying
it. Grab a children's book and read it
out loud. Acting out each character. Are
you able to separate characters and
actually keep the attention of the child
who's listening? Also, getting into a
good coaching program or maybe even
one-on-one coaching to give you some
feedback so that you know where to
course correct because a lot of people
find it very hard to self-direct.
Remember, your voice is a muscle and an
instrument. The more you use it with
intention, the better and better and
more confident you're going to be. Now,
let's talk about gear. And this is where
a lot of people get stuck. The internet
is full of people who are saying you
have to buy a $2,000 microphone and
build a completely soundproof booth to
get started in voice over. And nothing
has been further from the truth. Voice
acting is more about performance and
clarity versus how nice your mic is. A
good beginner microphone is going to
probably run you anywhere from $100 to
$200. And you can use that microphone
well into your career. Next up, you're
going to need some recording software.
And that recording software is called a
DAW or digital audio workspace. And it's
basically a way to record your analog
voice, turn it into a digital signal
that goes into your computer. Okay. Next
up is your recording space. And your
recording space is probably even more
important than your actual microphone. A
$2,000 microphone will still sound
terrible in a terrible recording space.
There are two things you need to worry
about when it comes to your recording
space. Keeping outside sound out and
inside noise dead. Remember, when it
comes to inside noise, the dead the
better. There are several ways you can
go when you're building your first
booth. The first way is what we call a
blanket fort. It's where you buy PVC
pipe, you create a frame, you get moving
blankets or even comforters and things
around your house to make a fort, and
that goes a very long way into treating
the space. Now, you still have to worry
about outside noise coming in, but that
does a really good job of deadening the
inside noise. The next step is if you
have a spare closet in your house, maybe
it's a walk-in closet, maybe it's got
clothing in it or not, you can dedicate
that closet to your recording space.
Next up is buying a dedicated booth like
the one you see here. Just keep in mind
this is going to set you back several
thousand dollar, but it's not required
to get started. The bottom line here is
don't let the equipment or lack of
equipment hold you back. Get some good
entry-level equipment and get started
and then later you can reinvest into
better equipment as you go. Okay, now
let's talk about some performance tips.
These tips are going to instantly help
your reads and help you sound more
professional. The first step is read
like you're talking to a friend. So,
picture a face in your mind. Maybe it's
your best friend or someone in your
family. How would you talk to them? Next
step is mark up your script. A lot of
times scripts need to be changed a
little bit. Not the words themselves,
but maybe you need to underline or bold
or highlight certain parts of the script
so that you can remember to emphasize
this part or do something different on
this other part. Next up is smile when
you talk. If you've got a read that
needs to be friendly and upbeat, when
you smile, people can hear it. All
right, this next one is avoid the DJ
voice. And this is something that I've
had to unlearn since when I started in
radio back in 95. People don't want to
hear a polished, professional, you know,
boommy radio sound. They want real and
natural. So, this is something once
again that I had to really work hard to
try to lose. The next tip is slow down.
And I'm going to say it again. Slow
down. For years, I had a sign above my
computer screen that said, "Slow down."
Because what ends up happening is as
soon as you sit down behind a microphone
and hit that record button, your
adrenaline starts to pump. And when your
adrenaline pumps, your heart goes faster
and everything speeds up. Try to
remember to slow down. Remember, clients
aren't going to hire you just to read
words on a page. You need to bring those
words to life. So, you've practiced and
practiced and practiced and gotten some
gear and built a decent recording place
in your house. Now, how do you go out
and actually find the work? Okay, there
are three main paths when it comes to
getting work in VO. The first is
freelance platforms, platforms like
Fiverr or Upwork. There you can kind of
start working with scripts and clients
and get a little bit of money going just
to kind of build your confidence in your
experience. Next up are pay-to-play
sites. And these are casting sites where
you pay a fee either yearly or monthly
and you get access to audition
opportunities. The third is direct
marketing. And this is where you reach
directly out to content creators, video
editors, and other places who create
video content that need voices. You
introduce yourself. You submit your
demos. And if they like it, they will
add you to their roster and start
hopefully sending you either jobs or
auditions. Now, I'd like to talk about
mindset and the mindset that you have to
have in this business. Being a voice
actor isn't about being perfect. It's
about being persistent. You are going to
stumble and you're going to play your
voice back and cringe. But just
remember, the more you practice, the
more you get good coaching and learn the
ropes, the better and better you're
going to be. Some voice actors audition
dozens of times before landing their
first job. And that's okay. The
difference between the people who quit
and the people who are successful in
voice acting is persistence. Try to
avoid the comparison game. And that's
listening to other voice actors and
thinking, "Wow, I'll never be as good as
they are. They were beginners at one
time as well." Go through the steps,
learn from others, practice, practice,
practice, be persistent, and you will
win. So, there's your quick road map on
how to become a great voice actor. even
if you don't have any experience.
There's lots of smaller steps in the
process, but these are going to be your
main steps to go ahead and start working
your way towards becoming either a
part-time or full-time voice actor. We
covered what voice acting actually is,
the kinds of equipment you need to get,
how to find the work, the different
kinds of work that are out there, and
the mindset to become successful. So, if
you've ever thought about becoming a
voice actor, what are you waiting for?
You can really get started even today.
Even if you don't have a microphone yet,
download Audacity. It's free. Start
recording yourself even with your cheap
mic on your computer. Start to play it
back and get used to hearing your own
voice. And remember, being great isn't
about having the greatest voice in the
world. It's about using your voice with
confidence, clarity, and connection.
Also, if you want to learn seven reasons
why right now is the best time to be a
voice actor, then click right here.